This is the skyline of my hometown, New Orleans.
هذه صورة لناطحات السحاب في مدينتي، نيو اورلينز.
It was a great place to grow up,
كانت مكانا جميلا للعيش فيه كصغيرة،
but it's one of the most vulnerable spots in the world.
ولكنه واحد من اكثر الامكنة المعرضة للخطر في العالم.
Half the city is already below sea level.
نصف المدينة تقع حاليا تحت مستوى البحر.
In 2005, the world watched as New Orleans
في 2005، شاهد العالم عندما دُمرت نيو اورلينز
and the Gulf Coast were devastated by Hurricane Katrina.
والشاطئ الخليجي في الولايات المتحدة من قبل الإعصار "كاترينا".
One thousand, eight hundred and thirty-six people died. Nearly 300,000 homes were lost.
1836 شخصا فقدوا ارواحهم. ودُمر ما يقارب 300,000 منزل.
These are my mother's, at the top --
البيت في الصور العليا هو بيت أمي ــ
although that's not her car,
ولكن السيارة ليست سيارتها،
it was carried there by floodwaters up to the roof --
فقد انجرفت بماء الطوفان التي كانت تعادي السقوف ــ
and that's my sister's, below.
والبيت في الصور السفلية هو بيت اختي.
Fortunately, they and other family members got out in time,
لحسن الحظ استطاعوا هم وافراد العائلة الاخرين مغادرة المنزل في الوقت المناسب،
but they lost their homes, and as you can see,
ولكنهم خسروا منازلهم، وكما تشاهدون،
just about everything in them.
خسروا كل شيء في الداخل.
Other parts of the world have been hit by storms
الاعاصير ضربت مناطق اخرى من العالم
in even more devastating ways.
بقوة أشد.
In 2008, Cyclone Nargis and its aftermath
في عام 2008، حصد الاعصار "نرجز" ومخلفاته
killed 138,000 in Myanmar.
ارواح 138,000شخص في ميانمار.
Climate change is affecting our homes, our communities,
التغييرات المناخية تؤثر على منازلنا، على مجتمعاتنا،
our way of life. We should be preparing
وعلى اسلوب حياتنا. علينا ان نجهز انفسنا
at every scale and at every opportunity.
بكل المقاييس وفي كل فرصة متوفرة.
This talk is about being prepared for, and resilient to
المغزى من هذا الحديث هو ان نجهز انفسنا، ونسعى للتكيف
the changes that are coming and that will affect our homes
مع التغييرات الاتية والتي ستطال منازلنا الشخصية
and our collective home, the Earth.
ومنزلنا الجماعي: الأرض.
The changes in these times won't affect us all equally.
التغييرات في الوقت الحالي لن تطالنا جميعا بنسبة متكافئة.
There are important distributional consequences,
فهنالك توزيعات مهمة لنتائج هذه التتغييرات،
and they're not what you always might think.
وهي لا تتطابق دائما مع توقعاتنا.
In New Orleans, the elderly and female-headed households
في نيو اورلينز، العجزة والبيوت المدارة من قبل النساء
were among the most vulnerable.
كانت الاكثر تضررًا.
For those in vulnerable, low-lying nations,
وإلى أولئك الذين يعيشون في دول منخفضة،
how do you put a dollar value on losing your country
هل تسطيعون تقييم خسارة بلدكم والاماكن التي
where you ancestors are buried? And where will your people go?
تستر جثث اجدادكم بقيم مالية؟ واين سيذهب شعبكم؟
And how will they cope in a foreign land?
وماذا سيكون مصيرهم في بلاد غريبة؟
Will there be tensions over immigration,
هل سيكون هناك خلافات حول قضايا الهجرة؟
or conflicts over competition for limited resources?
أو خلافات في تقسيم الموارد المحدودة؟
It's already fueled conflicts in Chad and Darfur.
هنالك حاليًا خلافات في هذه القضايا في التشاد ودارفور.
Like it or not, ready or not, this is our future.
هذا هو مستقبلنا، سواء احببتموه ام لا، إن كنتم مستعدين له ام لا.
Sure, some are looking for opportunities in this new world.
هنالك بالطبع البعض من الذين يبحثون عن الفرص في هذا العالم الجديد.
That's the Russians planting a flag on the ocean bottom
في الصورة، الروس يزرعون علمًا في قاع المحيط
to stake a claim for minerals under the receding Arctic sea ice.
ليسيطروا على المعادن تحت الثلج المتقهقر في البحر القطب الشمالي.
But while there might be some short-term individual winners,
ولكن بالرغم من وجود الاشخاص الذين سيستفيدون من التغييرالمناخي على المدى القريب،
our collective losses will far outweigh them.
إلا ان خسائرنا الجماعية ستكون أكبر بكثير.
Look no further than the insurance industry as they struggle
انظر مثلا الى سوق التأمين الذي يحاول
to cope with mounting catastrophic losses
التأقلم مع الخسائر المتزايدة
from extreme weather events.
إثر التزايد في شدة الكوارث الطبيعية.
The military gets it. They call climate change
الجيش يدرك المسألة جيداً. فهم يصفون التغيير المناخي
a threat multiplier that could harm stability and security,
بالخطر المتزايد الذي قد يُضر بالاستقرار والأمن،
while governments around the world are evaluating
بينما الحكومات في نطاق العالم يقيّيمون
how to respond.
الرد المناسب لتصدي العواقب.
So what can we do? How can we prepare and adapt?
اذا ماذا يمكننا ان نفعل؟ كيف يمكننا ان نجهز انفسنا ونتأقلم؟
I'd like to share three sets of examples, starting with
أود أن أطلعكم على ثلاث امثلة، بدئاً
adapting to violent storms and floods.
بالتأقلم مع عواصف شديدة وفيضانات.
In New Orleans, the I-10 Twin Spans,
في نيو اورلينز، تم اعادة بناء الجسرين التؤمين،
with sections knocked out in Katrina, have been rebuilt
والذين تضررا جزئيا في اعصار "كاترينا"،
21 feet higher to allow for greater storm surge.
21 قدما اعلى من السابق لكي لا يتضرروا في اعاصير مماثلة.
And these raised and energy-efficient homes
وتم بناء هذه البيوت العالية والتي تتمتع بإستخدام فعال للطاقة
were developed by Brad Pitt and Make It Right
من قبل "براد بيت" وجمعية "Make It right"
for the hard-hit Ninth Ward.
لحيّ (Ninth Ward) الذي اصيب بضرر شديد من قبل الاعصار.
The devastated church my mom attends has been
الكنيسة المحطمة والتي كانت ترتادها امي لم تُبنى فقط
not only rebuilt higher, it's poised to become
بأرتفاع اعلى، ولكنها ستصبح اول كنيسة
the first Energy Star church in the country.
مصنفة بنجمة الطاقة (Energy Star).
They're selling electricity back to the grid
الان، الكنيسة هي التي تقوم ببيع الكهرباء للشركة
thanks to solar panels, reflective paint and more.
بفضل لوحات الطاقة الشمسية، والطلاء العاكس، واشياء اخرى.
Their March electricity bill was only 48 dollars.
فاتورة الكهرباء التابعة لهم لشهر مارس/اذار كانت 48 دولاراً فقط.
Now these are examples of New Orleans rebuilding in this way,
هذه امثلة تمثل الكيفية التي قامت فيها نيو اورلينز ببناء نفسها،
but better if others act proactively with these changes in mind.
ولكن الافضل للآخرين ان يستجيبوا استباقياً مع هذه الغييرات في الاذهان.
For example, in Galveston, here's a resilient home
مثلا هذا منزل متكيف في كالفستون
that survived Hurricane Ike,
والذي نجا من اعصار "آيك"
when others on neighboring lots clearly did not.
بينما تحطمت البيوت المجاورة.
And around the world, satellites and warning systems
وحول العالم، فإن الاقمار الصناعية وأنظمة الإنذار المبكر
are saving lives in flood-prone areas such as Bangladesh.
تقوم بإنقاذ الحياة في الاماكن المعرضة للفيضانات كبنجلادش.
But as important as technology and infrastructure are,
ولكن رغم أهمية التقانة والبنية التحتية،
perhaps the human element is even more critical.
إلا إنّ الحاسة الإنسانية هي الحاسمة.
We need better planning and systems for evacuation.
نحن بحاجة الى التخطيط المبكر وأنظمة إخلاء متطورة.
We need to better understand how people make decisions
نحن بحاجة لإدراك كيفية تفكير الإنسان للوصول ا لى قرار
in times of crisis, and why.
في أوقات الشدة، ولمعرفة لماذا يجب أن نأخذ هذه القرارات.
While it's true that many who died in Katrina did not have access to transportation,
صحيح ان الكثيرين من الذين توفوا في اعصار "كاترينا" لم يكن لديهم اي فرص للتنقل،
others who did refused to leave as the storm approached,
ولكن العديد ايضا رفضوا المغادرة عقب الاعصار
often because available transportation and shelters
بسبب حيواناتهم الاليفة والتي لم تتمكن خدمات النقل
refused to allow them to take their pets.
والملاجئ من قبولها.
Imagine leaving behind your own pet in an evacuation or a rescue.
تصور ان تترك حيواناتك الاليفة وانت تغادر الى الامان.
Fortunately in 2006, Congress passed
لحسن الحظ وافق الكونجرس على
the Pet Evacuation and Transportation Standards Act (Laughter)
قانون لإخلاء ونقل الحيوانات الاليفة في الحالات الطارئة. (ضحك)
— it spells "PETS" — to change that.
لمنع تكرار الامر.
Second, preparing for heat and drought.
ثانيا، التأهب لمواجهة الحر والجفاف.
Farmers are facing challenges of drought from Asia
من اسيا الى افريقيا، من استراليا الى اوكلاهوما،
to Africa, from Australia to Oklahoma,
الفلاحون يواجهون تحديات الجفاف
while heat waves linked with climate change
بينما موجات الحر المرتبطة بالتغيير المناخي
have killed tens of thousands of people
قد حصدت عشرات الألاف الضحايا
in Western Europe in 2003, and again in Russia in 2010.
في غرب اوروبا في عام 2003 ومن ثم روسيا في 2010.
In Ethiopia, 70 percent, that's 7-0 percent of the population,
في اثيوبيا، 70% من السكان يعتمدون على
depends on rainfall for its livelihood.
المطر ليكسبوا رزقهم.
Oxfam and Swiss Re, together with Rockefeller Foundation,
الجمعيات "Oxfam" و "Swiss Re" بالاضافة الى "Rockefeller Foundation"
are helping farmers like this one build hillside terraces
يساعدون الفلاحين مثل هؤلاء الذين في الصورة في بناء مصاطب على منحدرات التلال
and find other ways to conserve water,
وايجاد طرق اخرى لخزن المياه،
but they're also providing for insurance when the droughts do come.
وهذه الجمعيات توفر ايضا التأمين في حال وقوع جفاف.
The stability this provides is giving the farmers
تؤدي هذه المشاريع الى اعطاء الفلاحين
the confidence to invest.
الثقة اللازمة لللإستثمار.
It's giving them access to affordable credit.
انها تعطي الفلاحين ائتمانات رخيصة
It's allowing them to become more productive so that
وتعطيهم الفرصة لكي يكونوا اكثر انتاجاً
they can afford their own insurance over time, without assistance.
ومع الوقت يصبحون قادرين على كسب التأمين بنفسهم من دون مساعدة.
It's a virtuous cycle, and one that could be replicated
انها دائرة الفضيلة، ومن الممكن اعادة تنفيذها في اماكن اخرى
throughout the developing world.
في بلدان نامية اخرى.
After a lethal 1995 heat wave
بعد موجة الحر المميتة في عام 1995
turned refrigerator trucks from the popular
والتي حولت الثلاجات في شاحنات مهرجان طعم شيكاغو
Taste of Chicago festival into makeshift morgues,
الشعبي الى مشرحات مؤقتة،
Chicago became a recognized leader,
اصبحت شيكاغو قائدا معتمدا
tamping down on the urban heat island impact
في خفض الحرارة في المناطق الحرارية
through opening cooling centers,
من خلال فتح مراكز التبريد،
outreach to vulnerable neighborhoods, planting trees,
والتواصل مع الأحياء المُعرضة للضرر، وزراعة الأشجار،
creating cool white or vegetated green roofs.
وخلق أسطح لمباني خضراء باردة أوصنع أسقف ذات غطاء نباتي.
This is City Hall's green roof, next to Cook County's [portion of the] roof,
هذا هو السقف الاخضر لبناء البلدية، بجانب [جزء من] سقف "Cook county".
which is 77 degrees Fahrenheit hotter at the surface.
وهو أكثر حرارة بمقدار 77 درجة فهرنهايتة على سطح.
Washington, D.C., last year, actually led the nation
في العام الفائت،العاصمة واشنطن كانت على رأس البلاد في
in new green roofs installed, and they're funding this in part
بناء اسقف خضراء مزروعة. انهم يمولون ذلك جزئيا
thanks to a five-cent tax on plastic bags.
بفرض خمس سنتات كضريبة على الاكياس البلاستيكية.
They're splitting the cost of installing these green roofs
انهم يتقاسمون تكلفة نصب هذه الاسقف الخضراء
with home and building owners.
مع مالكي المنازل والمباني.
The roofs not only temper urban heat island impact
السقوف لا تمنع فقط ظاهرة جُزر الإحترار في المناطق السكنية من الوقوع
but they save energy, and therefore money,
بل انها تخفض من استهلاك الطاقة، وبذلك توفر المزيد من النقود
the emissions that cause climate change,
والغازات التي تسبب تغييرات مناخية
and they also reduce stormwater runoff.
وهم يقلصون من جريان الماء السطحي في وقت العواصف.
So some solutions to heat can provide for win-win-wins.
لذا فإن بعض الحلول لمشاكل الحر تنتج ايضا حلولاً لمشاكل اخري.
Third, adapting to rising seas.
ثالثاً، التكيف مع نسبة مياه البحر المتصاعدة.
Sea level rise threatens coastal ecosystems, agriculture,
تصاعد نسبة المياه يشكل تهديدا للنظام الايكولوجي في الشواطئ، والفلاحة،
even major cities. This is what one to two meters
وحتى المدن الكبرى. هذا ما يحدث عند ازدياد مستوى سطح البحر
of sea level rise looks like in the Mekong Delta.
بمتر او مترين في دلتا "ميكونج".
That's where half of Vietnam's rice is grown.
هنا حيث يزرع نصف الأرز في فيتنام.
Infrastructure is going to be affected.
البنية التحتية ستتأثر.
Airports around the world are located on the coast.
كثير من المطارات في العالم مبنية بالقرب من الشواطئ.
It makes sense, right? There's open space,
يبدوا منطقيا اليس كذلك؟ فهناك فراغ شاسع
the planes can take off and land without worrying about
لكي تتمكن الطائرات من الاقلاع والهبوط من دون ان يقلقوا
creating noise or avoiding tall buildings.
بشأن البنايات العالية او التسبب بالضوضاء.
Here's just one example, San Francisco Airport,
هذا المثال، هو مطار سان فرانسيسكو،
with 16 inches or more of flooding.
مع 16 انشاً او اكثر من الفيضان.
Imagine the staggering cost of protecting
تخيل التكاليف المرتفعة لحماية
this vital infrastructure with levees.
هذا البناء الأساسي بإنشاء السدود حوله.
But there might be some changes in store
ولكن هنالك ايضا تغييرات اخرى قد تحدث
planes require more runway for takeoff
ستحتاج الطيارات الى مسافة اطول للإقلاع
because the heated, less dense air, provides for less lift.
لأن الهواء الاكثر سخونة والاقل كثافة يمد الطائرة بقوة رفع اقل.
San Francisco is also spending 40 million dollars
سينفق المطار ايضا 40 مليون دولار
to rethink and redesign its water and sewage treatment,
في اعادة تصميم وتغيير مجرى المياه والصرف الصحي،
as water outfall pipes like this one can be flooded with seawater,
فأنابيب الماء مثل تلك التي في الصورة تفيض بمياه البحر بسهولة،
causing backups at the plant, harming the bacteria
مما يزيد من نسبة المياه في شبكات الصرف، ويؤذي البكتريا
that are needed to treat the waste.
اللازمة لتحليل الفضلات.
So these outfall pipes have been retrofitted
لذا تم اعادة تصميم هذه الانابيب
to shut seawater off from entering the system.
لكي تمنع مياه البحر من الدخول.
Beyond these technical solutions, our work
غير هذه الحلول التقنية، لدينا عمل
at the Georgetown Climate Center with communities
في مركز جورج تاون للمناخ لتشجيع
encourages them to look at what existing legal and policy tools are available
المنظمات في النظر الى الادوات القانونية والبوليصية المتاحة
and to consider how they can accommodate change.
لدراسة كيفية استيعاب هذه التغييرات.
For example, in land use, which areas do you want
مثلا في البر، اي المناطق يمكن حمايتها
to protect, through adding a seawall, for example,
ببناء جدار برمائي،
alter, by raising buildings, or retreat from,
او تعديل المباني برفعها الى الاعلى، او إخلاء المناطق
to allow the migration of important natural systems,
المحاذية للماء لكي تعطي المجال لأنظم طبيعية بالنمو
such as wetlands or beaches?
كالاراضي الرطبة والسواحل؟
Other examples to consider. In the U.K.,
امثلة اخرى: في المملكة المتحدة،
the Thames Barrier protects London from storm surge.
حاجز "التيامز" المائي يحمي لندن من عواصف شديدة.
The Asian Cities Climate [Change] Resilience Network
وفي اسيا تسعى شبكة التأقلم المناخي في المدن الاسيوية الى
is restoring vital ecosystems like forest mangroves.
ترميم انظمة ايكولوجية مهمة كغابات "المنغروف".
These are not only important ecosystems in their own right,
هذه الانظمة الايكولوجية ليست مهمة بحد ذاتها فحسب،
but they also serve as a buffer to protect inland communities.
بل هي ايضا تعمل كمناطق حاجزة لحماية المناطق البرية.
New York City is incredibly vulnerable to storms,
مدينة "نيويورك" منطقة ضعيفة جدا امام العواصف،
as you can see from this clever sign, and to sea level rise,
كما تشاهدون من هذا اللاصق الذكي، وضعيفة امام
and to storm surge, as you can see from the subway flooding.
ارتفاع البحر، كما تشاهدون من فيضان محطة قطار الانفاق هذه .
But back above ground, these raised ventilation grates
ولكن بالعودة إلى السطح، فإن انظمة التهوية المرتفعة
for the subway system show that solutions can be both
لقطار الانفاق، تدل على ان الحلول تستطيع ان تكون
functional and attractive. In fact, in New York,
عملية وفاتنة في آن واحد. يحاول المصممين في نيويورك،
San Francisco and London, designers have envisioned
وسان فرانسيسكو، ولندن ان يصمموا طرقا
ways to better integrate the natural and built environments
لدمج البيئات الطبيعية والاصطناعية
with climate change in mind.
مع التغييرات المناخية.
I think these are inspiring examples of what's possible
هذه امثلة حية عن ماذا بوسعنا ان نفعل
when we feel empowered to plan for a world that will be different.
عندما نشعر بأننا مخولين للتخطيط لعالم سيكون مختلفًا.
But now, a word of caution.
والان، كلمة تحذير.
Adaptation's too important to be left to the experts.
التكيف هو موضوع اهم من ان يُترك للخبراء.
Why? Well, there are no experts.
لماذا؟ لانه ليس هناك خبراء.
We're entering uncharted territory, and yet
نحن ندخل في اماكن غير مكتشفة حتى الان، ولكن
our expertise and our systems are based on the past.
كل خبراتنا وأنظمتنا مبينة على احداث الماضي.
"Stationarity" is the notion that we can anticipate the future
"السكون" هو الفكرة القائلة بأننا يمكن أن نتوقع المستقبل
based on the past, and plan accordingly,
بتحليل الماضي، ثم التخطيط وفقا لذلك.
and this principle governs much of our engineering,
وهذا المبدأ يحكم معظم هندساتنا،
our design of critical infrastructure, city water systems,
وتصاميم الابنية الحساسة، ونظام المياه في المدن،
building codes, even water rights and other legal precedents.
وقوانين البناء، وحتى حقوق المياه والإجرائات القانونية الاخرى.
But we can simply no longer rely on established norms.
ولكننا لا نستطيع ببساطة الوثوق المعايير المعمول بها.
We're operating outside the bounds of CO2 concentrations
نحن نتصرف خارج حدود تركيز غاز ثاني أكسيد الكربون
that the planet has seen for hundreds of thousands of years.
الذي شهده الكوكب لمئات الآلاف من السنين.
The larger point I'm trying to make is this.
النقطة الكبيرة التي أحاول تحقيقها هي هذه.
It's up to us to look at our homes and our communities,
إن الأمر متعلق بنا لمراجعة بيوتنا ومجتمعاتنا،
our vulnerabilities and our exposures to risk,
ونقاط ضعفنا ومدى تعرضنا للمخاطر،
and to find ways to not just survive, but to thrive,
والبحث عن سبل ليس فقط للبقاء على قيد الحياة بل للإزدهار،
and it's up to us to plan and to prepare
والأمر متروك لنا للتخطيط والإعداد
and to call on our government leaders and require them
عوة قادة حكومتنا ومطالبتهم
to do the same, even while they address
القيام بالشيء نفسه، حتى حين يواجهون
the underlying causes of climate change.
الأسباب الكامنة وراء تغير المناخ.
There are no quick fixes.
لا توجد هنالك حلول سريعة.
There are no one-size-fits-all solutions.
لا توجد أي حلول تناسب الجميع.
We're all learning by doing.
نحن جميعا نتتعلم عن طريق التطبيق.
But the operative word is doing.
ولكن التطبيق المرتبط بالفعل.
Thank you.
شكرا. (تصفيق)